Guide to the Arthur Bernhard Recknagel Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Arthur Bernhard Recknagel papers
1904-1960
MS 408
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6
Correspondence, writings, subject files, account books, photographs, an album of postcards, clippings, and printed matter of Arthur Bernhard Recknagel. The largest part of the collection is made up of papers, speeches, and reports by Recknagel and others on forestry. Also included are records of the St. Regis Paper Company for which Recknagel had been forestry consultant and a number of reports prepared by the Committee on Conservation and Management of Natural Resources of the National Association of Manufacturers (1952-1958). The small amount of family correspondence dates from 1951-1956.
Recknagel, A. B. (Arthur Bernhard), 1883-1962
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the School of Forestry, 1962.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Arthur Bernhard Recknagel died August 8, 1962. He was born in Brooklyn, N.Y., December 15, 1883. He prepared for Yale at Adelphi Academy, Brooklyn. After graduation Arthur went to the Yale Forestry School, making Sigma Xi (the scientific honor society) and graduating magna cum laude in 1906. He went directly into the government forestry service and was successively Forest Assistant (1906-7), Chief of Reconnaissance on National Forests of the West (1907-8), Chief of Silviculture, Southwestern District (1908-10) and Assistant District Forester with headquarters at Albuquerque, N. Mex. (1910-13). During the academic year 1911-12 he travelled abroad, studying the forests of northern Europe. In 1913 he was called to the Professorship of Forest Management and Utilization at Cornell, becoming later Chairman of the Department and retiring in 1943, to become a consulting forester. Meanwhile he had held visiting professorships at California and the University of British Columbia and had published many articles and books of high distinction in the field of Forestry. During the Second World War he was Area Forester at Albany for the War Production Board.
Arthur was President of the Northwestern Wood Utilization Council, Vice-president and Director of the Empire State Forest Products Association, Technical Director of Forestry for the St. Regis Paper Company. As supervisor of two million acres of timberland all over the United States he traveled widely but still contributed more than his share to the welfare of his own community. He was a vestryman of St. John's Episcopal Church in Ithaca and chairman of the Cornell University Christian Association.
Arthur was married in 1909 to Mary Thomas Miller of Harrisburg, Va. They have two sons: Bernard W., born in 1912, and Thomas M., born in 1918. After the death of his first wife Arthur married Miss Helen Johnston who survives him. Mrs. Recknagel lives at 107 Cayuga Heights Road, Ithaca, N.Y.
--Clarence Mendell, Secretary of the Class of 1904
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, writings, subject files, account books, photographs, an album of postcards, clippings, and printed matter of Arthur Bernhard Recknagel. The largest part of the collection is made up of papers, speeches, and reports by Recknagel and others on forestry. Also included are records of the St. Regis Paper Company for which Recknagel had been forestry consultant and a number of reports prepared by the Committee on Conservation and Management of Natural Resources of the National Association of Manufacturers (1952-1958). The small amount of family correspondence dates from 1951-1956.
Conservation of natural resources; Environmental protection; Forests and forestry; Lumber trade; Foresters; Recknagel, A. B. (Arthur Bernhard), 1883-1962; St. Regis Paper Company
- Inventory
  - Family correspondence, Circa 1951-1956 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence, A-U, Circa 1946-1953 (Box 1)
  - Writings, Circa 1904-1944 (Box 1)
  - Subject file, with MS tables of contents scattered throughout: correspondence, MSS, printed matter (Box 1)
    - Forest Industries Council (national and New York State), Circa 1944-1958 (Box 2)
    - National Association of Manufacturers: Committee on Conservation and Management of National Resources, Circa 1952-1958 (Box 2)
    - National Association of Manufacturers: Committee on Conservation and Management of National Resources, Circa 1952-1958 (Box 3)
    - New York State: various papers on forestry, Circa 1918-1953 (Box 3)
    - St. Regis Paper Co., Circa 1948-1960 (Box 3)
    - St. Regis Paper Co., Circa 1948-1960 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1933-1934, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
  - Account book, Circa 1953-1958 (Box 5)
  - Album of postcards, undated (Box 5)
  - Photographs, 1904-1950, undated (Box 5)
  - Oversize photographs, 1905-1953 (Box 6)
  - German newspapers, 1940-1945 (Box 6)